Of the course of large language model for software engineer. I mean through all these labs. What we are going to do is to learn a little bit about Llms: how to prepare a training of Llm. How to prepare a fine-tuning of llm. How to use deploy an llm. Quantize an llm. In general.
I mean everything related to coding stuff related to Llms.
For what concern the laboratories? You can find all the laboratories of this course in the Github Repository. So if you go to the repository of Dbdmg. Inside the repository of large language model. Llm: You can find all the laboratories that we are going to deal with.
Along these months. But what concerned the very 1st laboratory? Actually, we are not going to do anything related to actual Nlp or large language models, because this will be more an introductory introduction laboratory to the actual use of a machine learning or AI pipeline. So.
How to deal with the data, how to deal with the training pipeline. How to deal with Pytosh. That is one of the most famous libraries. When you want to code machine learning and so on. But we will see that there are many staff, and there are many principles.
There can be directly carries from normal machine learning. So when we have data sets that are composed by tables, numbers or images, 2 actual natural language process, machine learning pipelines.
Just a couple of info before starting. Since this is the second edition that I will give of these laboratories. Of course I would appreciate a lot of feedback from you. So I already have given this laboratory last year.
And while students of the last year told me actually is the fact that instead of presenting the solution, what they would like to have is to completely laboratory together. Okay.
On the other side. The main problem of this laboratories is the fact that we try to compress a lot of information is just 1 h and a half, so it will be a trade-off, of course, more time will lose. To well, explain everything inside the laboratory on the other side. It means that it will need more work.
From your side, maybe from home, or after the actual laboratory, to actually conclude, or already see the lab before coming here. The lab of today will be quite short, and it will be composed only by one laboratory. So one only one exercise.
Only one notebook, but starting from the next one. Every laboratory will have 2 parts. Okay.
And you will see that all these laboratory the good thing is the fact that they are quite self explanatory. So what does it mean is that even without me you should be able to go through heat, understand the main principle, and solve the problems.
If Github wants to help me and load. But anyway, how the lab is composed is that there we you have several exercises. There are some parts of the code that are already written, okay, and instead time to time there are some parts.
With the to-do in which the simple thing that you have to do is to try to solve the problem that you have there in order to continue to run the notebook. Okay.
So my suggest from now on, and what I would like to try with these laboratories. But of course, I beg you please. If you have any feedback, not only at the end of the course, but also during the course please give it to me in such a way that I mean you can gain the most, and I can give you the most.
Out of these laboratories. But what I ask you is starting from the next labs, and next week, and I think also, the week after the next one we will not have a lab actually, but my session is to come here already. Knowing the lab so.
Give a look to the lab, try to solve it. Try to see if there are any problems in such a way that if you have any question you can ask me so the idea would be something like I will solve together with you without going to. I mean not going to the solution, but just giving you.
I mean solving together the lab of one of them. Okay. So, for example, T. 5, or attention in this case, and then, with the remaining time, we can all start the second laboratory. So the second part of the laboratory sorry, or if you have any question about the labs that you have solved at home. Of course you can ask me, and I can help.
Figuring it out.
These was the first, st the info.
I wanted to give you about the second one. I want to leave the floor for 5 min, and not more than 5 min to the actual team leader of Malto Malto is one of the student groups of Polytechnic of stewing. I think they already heard about students group in general, sadly. You are already very likely, in your last year of your master's degree.
But anyway, Malto is the machine learning group of polytechnic of 2 in a deal with a lot of tough challenges. Very, very fun. Group. I've been part of it in the past. So I will give you the floor to Eiberg that is the actual team leader of Malto that he will introduce you.
Very quick. We quickly the team, and also some of the events that we are organizing. Thank you.
Thank you, Claudio, for the introduction. Hello, everyone. I'm Albert Munis. I'm also the second year of.
Degree in data science. I'm also taking this course, and today I will present the Maltaur Machine Learning student team in Polytecnico and our events and our challenge, basically, our 1st goal is participating international machine and competitions like they are giving a real-world problem to solve. And we are doing six-month research about the problem.
And after that we are generating a solution, and we are publishing a sitefic paper in the conferences of the challenges. Our main goal is that but besides of it, we are trying to improve the AI community and the polytechnical editorial. Last year we started workshops. Maybe some of you heard them.
After that we are doing a lot of.
Events like malt talks. I will. I will tell you about the details, because we have a very close Maltalks. Here, basically, we are trying to.
Create new data, science and machine learning projects and try to publish and present them in the conferences.
These are, or some pasta achievements we have. Like you can see our supervisors there. One of them is Claudio, and one of them is, of course, the dear Professor Joe Bargia, basically, during the machine learning challenge they are supervising. Us.
Before any challenge that we have during the solutions during the problems. And,
Through a lot of stuff there helping us. And this one is the During the Ecml. Pgt. This year we won the Omnirna challenge there, and we presented our solution in Naples today.
And, as I told we have workshops also. This is the 1st version of the workshop that we did in a previous May this year. We will also organize some workshops about the basics Llms: basic, deep learning, and also we want to expand them for the reinforcement, learning, computer vision, or the some other
Common AI topics. The date is Tbd. But we will announce as soon as possible. Besides of the workshops, we are also organizing MoD talks. We are inviting the sector professionals to give speech about the latest AI topics. This was Ellen. He's a senior researcher in Intesa San Paulo, and he gave his speech about the mesh mechanism, interpretability in what Llms. And Machine Learning.
And in on this Friday we are inviting Professor Gushen arit. She is a professor from Istanbul Technical University, and she is the head of the Nlp. Lab of Istanbul Technical University. She will give a speech about the rag systems. Rag systems is.
Basically a document retrieval system for the Llms. And it would be a very interesting talk. We are. You are all invited, and we are waiting you, for on this Friday it will be at.
4 Pm. In Silicon fanat Luigi Ciminera. It's it will be in the Darwin.
And if you have any questions about the malto, you can scan this QR. Code, and you can text us on Instagram Linkedin, whenever you want or send them. Send us an email. So please welcome on Friday and have a nice lecture. Thank you, Claudio.
Okay.
So.
I would say, We can start with the lab. Can you still hear me? Yeah, of course you cannot see, but because I was not.
Sharing anything, yet hopefully.
But yeah, I will start to share from now on.
Of course.
Yisha.
Okay, a lot of info go away. Go away.
Okay, can you see? And can you hear me online.
Yes. Yes. Okay. Thank you very much.
Okay.
For your mental sanity.
The 1st thing that I will do is.
Maybe I've been something like that.
And maybe something like that can help.
Okay.
So I think that you can see better the laboratory, of course, as I already have said, you can find these laboratories online. Okay, so I suggest you to go through the laboratory together with me for what's concerned this 1st laboratory? It will not be very, very, very practical, but it will be more a theoretical kind of laboratory, because I mean, I will just introduce you the main.
Libraries that are related to machine learning. But the main thing that I want to show you today is how you should deal with a machine learning pipeline, as I already said, because, of course, when we talk about machine learning pipelines, we have to deal with several stuff. Okay, that are the models that are the data we have to organize the data. Somehow we have.
Organizing and training pipeline. Somehow we have to organize the validation steps, etc, etc. And the good thing is that when we talk about these pipelines they work more or less or exactly in the same way across different domain. Okay? So we changed the kind of data we change the kind of model. But at the end of the day the most of the things that we do.
Are the same across the different domain. So if we talk about tabular data, if we talk about text, if we talk about images at the end of the day we are talking about the same thing. Okay.
So in the lab of today, as I already said, we will deal with mainly tabular data and image data. Okay, just to give you a hint of how pytorch works. And what is Pytorch Pytorch is the main library that every AI or machine learning engineer used. Okay, it allows you to this with everything that is related to.
To to a machine learning pipeline.
And today we are going to see what is a tensor, what is a data loader? What is a neural network, and so on, and how to build everything of them. So let's start from the easiest possible element that we have in Pytosh. That is the tensor.
Okay, the tensor is nothing else. That an umpire. How many of you know, Numpai? I hope all of you.
Please raise your hands, please. I ask you to participate to the lecture, if you want, of course, and do every question you want also do in the lecture. Okay, so that I avoid just to talk to a world for 1 h and a half anyway. The good thing of the tensor of fighters is that they are very, very, very similar to the Numpaya race. Okay? With the only difference that they allow to have something extra that is required to actually build a machine learning or an AI model.
The main. The main 2 extra things that I would say at tensor has. The 1st one is that it automatically handles with the automatic differentiation, because, as you have already seen in the 1st lecture when we talk about training a model.
What we do is simply backpropagation of some derivatives over some loss function of the error that we have so the good thing of Pytch is that he deals with all the hard mathematical parts of the models backpropagation.
etc, by its own. So we don't have to do anything. Okay, just know that it exists. Okay? And the second thing very important is that it supports Gpu acceleration.
As you know, especially for what concerns large language model. If we want to train them, we need gpu because we need parallel ization. When we train the models, there are a lot of multiplication between mattresses, and we will see that everything at the end of the day, also inside a very big.
È very fancy. Large language model is at the end of the day, just a multiplication between 2 matrixes. The good thing is that Gpus parallelize very well. This kind of operation.
So as we can see there, we have a couple of tensor we can define. The tensor is in this way. So tor dot tensor comma. And here we define our tensor. We can do basic operation between tensors. So, for example, we have the sum, and here we have one plus 4, that is 5 plus 2 plus 5, that is, 7, and so on.
And here we can see the very 1st interesting thing. Okay, we are going to talk a lot about precision along this course. Because precision is very important.
In UN paio the default position is float 64. Okay, instead. Here in Pytorch the default precision is float 32.
I would say that now in when we deal with large language models when we deal with Nlp. The most common precision that you will see, or the maximum precision you will see, is B. Floats 16. Actually.
What is the principle? The principle is the fact that we are not losing a lot of precision. Okay? And now they are like putting the number inside the arrays in such a way that they are optimized for training the model and use the models.
But anyway, what is interesting for us is the fact that at the price of losing a little bit of position that at the end of the day doesn't change a lot. The final behavior of the model. What we gain is much more speed up in the computation. Okay.
And, in fact, what we can see here is that if we create a couple of mathises that are even small, I would say, because they are 1,000 per 1,000. Okay? And if yes.
Zoom more. Yeah, of course I can.
Is it better.
Okay. Amazing online. One message I can. I can't find the lab files on Dbdmg: Okay, I mean all the the repository you can find it on Github.
I mean, let let me share you one sec. On the.
All the desktop.
Okay, you you can find all the laboratories there. There is not yet the link I noticed this morning. There is not yet the link on the page. I will put it there also. But anyway, if you go on the Github page of Dbdmg. And if you go under Llm: there are already all the labs.
Okay.
Let me know if you can, if you manage to find it. I hope so.
Okay, but anyway, if we decide to do a multiplication even between these 2 quite small matrices.
What we find out is that, okay, let me.
This is the solution. Sorry? No, no, no, no, I don't want the solution.
Okay.
Okay, even between these 2 relatively small matrices, and imagine that I mean for each forward pass of an Llm. We have.
I think thousands and thousands and thousands of operations like this.
We can see already a big difference in time computation. If we do a multi, a material multiplication between a float, 64, and a float 32. That is the reason why in machine learning.
We always talk about maximum flows 32, and I would say, now in Nlp we talk maximum about float 16. This is not only related, of course, to how fast the model is in doing the inference.
By the other. Very important thing is the fact that Gpu, as we know, doesn't have a lot of memory. What does it mean? It means that for every parameter we have, we need half the number of bytes to actually store the parameter.
It means that we kind of with the same amount of gpu vram: the double amount of the parameters. Okay. So the second main problem is the fact that these large language models have to fit inside the Vram of Gpus that are super expensive.
And so everything that we can spare almost at a free course. We want to do so so. These are the main 2 rationales. Why, we prefer to have a lower precision and index is something called quantization. So even to go lower than float 16.
When we actually try to deploy our models. But we will talk about quantization and all this stuff in the next laboratories.
So for what's concerned Torch, as I already said, the default, the type is float 32. Of course, if you want you can change, the d-type of your array. Okay, of your tensor. Sorry to do so is enough to cast it, you can cast it in 2 different ways using the 2. Okay.
So array dot 2, and then you select the d type, the d-type that you prefer, or you can select it in this way.
Double. It means double precision.
So let's start from a very, very simple neural network. Okay, the most basic neural network that you know. That is something like this one: so that is that we have an input. Okay? And we want to learn a function, a linear function. Okay.
So simply this line: decide to interpolate all our training data points in such a way that then, when we receive a new point, and we want an estimate of this new point. We can actually use the weights and the biases that we have learned in order to.
Give back a prediction. Okay.
So the most basic linear layer is composed by 2 parameters.
Ha moltiplicative weights. That is this one: that is the one that controls the slope and then an additiv bias. Okay, they simply add the bias. So it shifts the actual line.
Let me go back there.
So what do we have? We have an input. We have a waiter bias, so a model let's call it model already, composed by 2 parameters, and then we have our output prediction. So let's start with the 1st definition of our most simple.
Neural network that we can have. That is a simple linear model. Okay, that is the one that I just described to you when we talk about linear model. What we have to do is to call from nn module. Okay, the simple linear model. Every time that we build actually.
And your network, we will have something similar to this. Okay, so we have to create a module. Okay? The module has 2 main functions that are the init and the forward. What do we do in the init is simply that we define. So we build our model so all the blocks that are inside our model.
Are inside the init. What do we mean with all the blocks? We mean that if we have a stack of different linear layer. Here is the place in which I want to declare each linear layer that is in my in my model.
Imagine, for example, if we have, I don't know. The attention inside our model here is where we define the attention. If we have a transformer here is where we define the transformer, and so on.
So here we put all the building blocks that are part of my neural network. Okay? And in this case, since we have simply a simple linear layer. What I would do is to define the self dot linear. Okay? The super is something that you have always to call, but you know.
Better than me. Then we call our simple. We create our simple linear layer that we are going to call in our forward, and I'm going to explain you shortly what a forward is.
That we can define like this. So here we define a normal linear layer in which we can put 2 information. So which one is the input and which one is the output of our linear layer. And that's it. Okay. We will start with the example that I've shown you in the image so.
Once we expect is one input. We want to try to make the model. So our linear model to learn a very basic function. Okay.
And so we want just one output.
Okay.
Then we have the forward.
The forward also is, of course, very, very important, is every time that we feed a piece of data or a batch of data to our model. Okay? So every time that we call our model to get a prediction what we do at the end of the day is to do the forward. Okay.
Because we have something like forward we get the prediction and then the back propagation. That's why they are called like that.
So the forward in this case is very easy, because, as I already said, what we expect is one input data. That is our X. Okay, we want our input data. That is just one number right now, inside our linear layer. Okay.
That is what we do here, and then we have our output. Okay, that is the returns simply.
Is everything clear until now.
Okay, please stop me at any moment, and.
Yes, I already said, please give me a lot of feedbacks. I mean not right now, especially if they are negative. But then, at the end of the lecture, if you want to come.
We can discuss about this.
So.
Now that we have defined our simple linear model. Okay.
We can simply create it like that. Okay? So we create our model as a simple linear model 1 point. And here we can do several stuff. The 1st thing as we expect is that after I create my model. Okay, if I try to call it. I have something like that. So I have my model that is composed by one linear layer. Okay, that expects one input feature and one out, and it will give back one output. Okay.
Here bias is equal to, and then we will see also a couple of other interesting things.
That are.
The very 1st one is the fact that we can call also every single element that is inside our model. So, for example, here we have only one linear layer, but I can call my linear layer like that.
And as we expect one input feeder, one output feature. And, as I said.
Every.
I mean, this kind of linear layer has one weight and one bias, and so we can also access to the actual weight. And of course, if we want.
To the actual bias. That is only one. Okay.
One interesting thing that you can, you may notice here is the fact that of course here everything is a tensor from now on everything will be a tensor. Okay, but the second interesting thing is: this requires grad equal to 2. What requires grad means.
Simply the fact that when we do the forward, if one waits, or one layer, or all the model has a required grad equal to 2. What does it mean is that it will automatically evaluate the gradient.
We will see then what does it mean? And then estimate the loss, function, and everything else that is needed for the training. So what does it mean when required? Grad is equal to 2. What we are saying to the model is okay. We need all the gradient information to be stored inside the model, because very likely, at some point I will do a backdrop.
Back propagation and.
So you have to update your weights. Of course, if we want, we can also turn off our required drive. For example, in the case we only are doing an inference. So imagine that you have trained your beautiful model. Okay, so you have your model you. And now you want us to use it. Okay? To make inference.
Of course, what I suggest you to do is to turn off the required glad because it's useless, additional useless additional operations that we don't need. Okay, we just need the gradient.
In the moment in which we are doing a training. Okay, at inference start evaluating every time. The gradient is useless. Of course.
Okay. So I showed you the Alinear layer. Looks like that. Okay? And this is the case in which we have one input and one output.
I want to make you a couple of questions.
The very 1st one is this one. So imagine that now I tried to configure my model in this way.
What doesn't mean that I configure the model in this way I put the 5 and the one.
Yes, exactly. We have 5 d. Inputs, and we have one output. Okay.
So? How do you think.
I mean I don't know if you can answer to this question. But how do you think the number of weights, and the number of biases will change. Now that I have a model that actually requires 5 inputs to give back only one output.
Amazing.
I'm useless there. So waits 5 weights. Okay? And one bias.
Exactly as we expect. Okay, because every weight is applied every time at every input. Okay, then the bias is something that is added only at the very end. What does it mean? It means that if we want, if I want.
A linear model that requires one input and 5 outputs.
Which one is the number of weights and biases that we expect in this case.
One wait, and I say Yes.
One. Wait.
And how many biases.
Okay, Because what we have to imagine in this case is something like, you are parallelizing. Okay, your data. So you have any way 5 ways. But now you have it in this way, because imagine that you have one piece of data, 1st weight, second bias, because spoiler.
Also the bias now will be 5. So go to the 1st way and then the 1st bias, then the same data. Second, wait. Second bias: the same data. 3rd wait solid bias. And so on.
Okay, amazing.
Now let's talk about the device.
And I have to speed up. Let's talk about the device. The device of torch is what makes it very, very, very easy. Okay, all I mean, all the sense of torch is to make your life easier. Okay, if you want, you can do everything AI-related. So backpropagation handling of data, handing of gpu, etc.
Wind numpy, of course, but of course it would be ahead. So the good thing of torch is that it makes your life easier under every aspect. And another way that touch has to make your life easier is to handling in a totally automatic way how to deal with your devices. Okay. So if you have to use a CPU, if you have to use a Gpu multiple Gpus.
Everything is handled by torch, and in particular is handled by the torch device. Okay.
Issues. Say, for example, to go on Google Collab in case you don't have a gpu in your laptop. You will see that you will be able to actually catch a gpu. That is what we call here Cuda. Okay. So when the device is in Cuda mode.
It means that we are using our gpu.
Thanks to this very, very easy line of code. Okay, so let's split it in 2 parts. The 1st one is this one: so here the 1st thing that we are asking to the model.
I simple this one: okay, touchdot.is available. So what I asking to touch is, can you see my gpu.
And if it's returned to okay, because, of course, I'm not using my laptop here. But our computer.
Touch. Tell me, okay, I can't see a gpu. So if you want, you can use this gpu okay? And then what I can do is that when I define Tosh device Cuda: okay, that is exactly what we do here. What I'm telling to the model. Is that okay? Now, everything that I have.
If I want, I can move it to the gpu, because, of course, when I create a tensor on its own default is on CPU is on CPU. But the good thing is that I can move everything. I want to Gpu simple, simply like that. Okay. So when I do, the 2.
Device that in this case is not anymore a caste. This is interesting. I mean, they use the exact same methods. But now it's a device that one attempt pass into the model and telling, Okay, now, my model, after this command is.
Inside a gpu. So it's using Qda.
Okay, so let's try to move our simple linear model to the device. So to Cuda. I mean, this is the game of the weights and biases that we already did.
Now, what we want to do is to make the model learn a linear function. Okay, but before doing this we need 2 additional elements to know the criterion and the optimizer.
The criteria that is very likely better known as loss function is what we use to evaluate the error in the prediction that we are making.
Why does it mean.
As we already said, when we want to train a neural network, what we do is we do the forward. We compute the gradients. Okay, then we estimate an error in some way, because, of course, this is the main difference that we have.
Between the different data domain, because, of course, in a classification problem how we estimate the error is totally different, for example, from a regression problem. Okay.
For example, here we have a simple regression problem. And so one way that we can have here to assess the error is simply the mean square error. So what do we do is that with our data we evaluate.
The dance between the prediction that my mother could do. For example, in this case, if X is equal to minus one and a half. My model in this time would produce something close to 0 . Okay, the actual true value is.
Something close to minus 0 point 5. And so I compute the minus square error simply like that. Okay, I have my prediction so my expected value, what I would like my model to produce. I have what the model actually is producing from here I can evaluate my loss so.
How big is the mistake that my model is doing. Okay.
Cross-entropy instead is a way of computing the loss. So it's simply a loss function that is used in classification. Okay? And little spoiler. Large language models are just, very, very giant classification models.
Because what they do at the end of the day is to predict the next most likely token. So, for example, a Cosenza pillos is something that you can use when you train your Llm: Okay, instead, of course, means square error is for a different kind of problem. This is the regression problem.
Then we have the optimizer. I'd like to introduce the optimizer as the
Piece of the whole that tell the model how much to move during its training.
What else it means.
When we do the forward okay, we estimate our error, then we do the backpropagation, and in this way we have a gradient. We can.
Configure our gradient as a simple direction. So where the weight and this is applied to every single weight where the weight of my model should move so in which direction should move.
In order to solve better the problem that I am having. Okay. So who is the one that tells my model how to solve it better the loss function, because I mean the loss function is cheating, and already knows which one is the right solution.
Through the bank propagation. What we do is to get this direction, now that we have the direction we have to make through every weight of my model a step in that direction.
But of course I can make a very small step. I can make a giant step, so.
How do I choose this step, and how the step is chosen.
Is, thanks to the optimizer. Okay.
So, for example, when you hear about the learning rate, have you already heard about learning grades.
Okay, is the rate at which the model is learning. So what does it mean? It's simply.
How long this step should be. What does it mean at the end of the day, if I have a big learning grade. It means that every time that I update the model the model move a lot. Okay.
What is the risk? Of course the risk is that since we are on an optimisation plane, if I make every time very huge step. The risk is that I never. I will never manage to find a minimum. Okay. So we just go around on this lost landscape, while never reaching a natural minimum.
Also because especially modern mush I mean machine learning theory and AI theory. What we do is that we never compute the so-called and good, old, pure, gladiant descent. Because in the past what happened when we wanted to solve a problem is that. Okay, I have this amount of data. I use all this data. I compute the gradient, and then I move in this direction.
Then with a newer model, and with the fact that we are training this model with billions of data. Of course it's impossible to.
Evaluate the gradient descent, the perfect gradient descent of all the data of my training data set. So what do we do is to split our training data set in the so-called mini batches or batches.
So very small groups. Okay, with some data inside them. And so what we say is that instead of making a few steps. Okay, but that are totally informative of them. Of the training data set.
What I do is that, ok? I take 64 piece of data. I evaluate the I do the forward I do the back prop, and then I make a very, a smaller step. Okay.
And it is exactly the idea of stochastic guardian descent. Okay, so stochasticity comes exactly from there.
Adam is simply an advance of stochastic gradient descents. Because then, with Adam, what we say is not simply okay. I use a small learning grade, so I make a small step, or I use a big learning grade, so I make a huge step.
Okay.
But then there are some things that are some additional information that we are carrying in the model in such a way that we try to make the learning the training of the model more stable. For example, very stupid case. Imagine that there is some weight that.
At some point if the training starts to going crazy. So while you adopt is that I do have forward, and it asked me to do the forward in one direction. Then the forward after it asked me to go in the opposite direction, forward after opposite direction again. So it means that the weight is going randomly.
Forward them backwards.
With Adam. One of the good things of Adam is that when he noticed this kind of movement that is very strange. It tried to dampen the update of the weight. So it's automatically, let's say, to make the learning weight a bit a little bit lower.
In such a way that then the step is smaller, and maybe the ways we finally find is minimum.
Okay? Is this part clear? Because I mean the optimizer and the loss functions or the criterion. The optimizer, as you may imagine is something that you absolutely need for every training and fine-tuning of every AI model that you.
Would like to develop.
So it's very important to have and to fully understand what a loss function is, what a criterion is. Why, it's important, of course, depending on our problem to select a different criterion. So a different loss function. And then the importance of the optimizer.
Okay.
If this is clear. Now, we are going to talk about data. Okay, how to handle the data.
As I already said.
The good thing of torch is that it makes our life much easier. And this is also related to our data. Okay.
So when we are talking about when I will use, I mean very, very little, the blackboard, because I know that online you cannot see. But I will do very, very basic drawing. So I mean it's not even necessary, very likely, to have it. But when we have a data set.
What we have is something like that. So imagine that we want okay to make our.
To make our model.
Learn a function. Okay, as I said, we have a learned model. Okay, so let's imagine. I don't know that I want my model to learn this function 5 weeks, plus 3 equal. Okay.
So what happened in this case is that I have my X. That is my input. Ok, imagine I have my input equal to one. Of course, my Y, that is the expected output that I would like query for my model is 8, okay.
If it is 2 ap. And p. 13. And so on. Okay.
So this.
Pending. For example, our 3 data set we call it data set. There are simply in a fibula form.
All the piece of information that we need, of course, is a data set also.
If we add.
As F.
The image of a cups.
And that's why they didn't work properly. Also leads. I mean a collection of cards.
With the Y of impact account. You'll also visit our data center. We don't have to have numbers. Okay? So also different if we see that a data set can also be. If, for example, in question answering our X can be, a normal question.
And the model to produce as outputs.
Okay. So the data set is simply all our data that we have okay collected together.
Hello! Let me go here now in the code.
So what do we want to do here is to create our very 1st data set. That is exactly the 1st one that I showed you here. So.
We have a series of input features that we are going to call them. X. Okay.
And it will be a tensile of shape. Number of points expected in our training data set.
One, because it's simply a vector. And then for each of our XI want to produce the target label expected, so have at the end something like that. But as 2 separate tensors okay.
So.
Of course.
Of course I have to deactivate copilot.
Because otherwise it's going to do the lab for me.
Housing. That this should be enough.
Okay.
It's not enough apparently.
But it says Ghost text suggest, but it's not ghost in them is.
Sorry.
Snoozer. I didn't.
For 5 min. I mean, it's better than nothing. Thank you very much.
Okay. So one of the good things of
beautiful! Another good thing of torch is that, of course it can create, also tensor of random numbers because one thing that I didn't say to you is the fact that even when we, are initializing, for example, a model. Okay.
Here. What we have here at the end of the day are just a bunch of tensor. Ok.
That's the thing at the end of the day waits is a tensile of dimension. 11 bias is a tensile of Dimension 11. And of course, before our training, all the parameters. So all the weights and all the biases of my models are randomized.
Okay, because they are not carrying in any interesting information. Okay? And of course, what we want to do through the training is to move the model in such a way that we start to learn what we would like to make it learn. So here. What I do is.
To create simplanx that is like that.
And then for the Y. What we would like to have is to.
Is to have the same function that we have here.
Plus 3. And then okay, let's say that we want a little bit of noise, okay, because otherwise the model will just learn by Hertz exactly what I was.
So attach that one, then.
And then.
One: okay.
So.
We can create our data set with a tensor data set. And I want to show you the data set first.st
Of course.
Okay. So our tensor data set is expect as an input.
2 elements the X that are our input data set. So the one that we are going to put inside our model and the Y. So the expected output. So when we create our data sets.
I mean, for what concern tensor data set at least we have a tensor data set is composed as we can expect.
Bye to 10, sir. Okay.
And then this 1st one is the tensile of our axis, and this second one is the tensor of our ys. Then with this very.
For common. That is shape. We can say the shapes of our tensors. Okay. So the X, as we expect, is the number of points one.
The one on the left, and the second one is of the same shape of hopefully.
And while we can already notice here is that this.
Tensor map exactly the function that we would like to add, okay, because, for example, the very 1st number minus 1.5. If we multiplied by 5 we get something close to 8.5.
Okay, minus 8.5. Then we add 3, and we get something close to minus 5.5. So.
Our 10. So that doesn't make sense.
Then the second important thing is the data loader. What I already have told you when we talk about stochastic, gradient descent is the fact that.
When we want to train our model. What we do is that we don't make the forward over the full training data set and then make the backward over the full training data set. But what we do is to select some batches of our data set. What does it mean?
When we, when we train a model. Ok, what happened? Usually something like that.
I have my full data sets that in this case is of 2,000 fourteen-eight.
Let's say 2,048 is okay.
What do we do along? Our training is that instead of using all of them together.
I select the so-called batch size. So the sides of our badge equal to let's say, 64. Okay.
So what happened.
Phone number. I mean what we would like compared in a normal trading type thing. We have our duty food model.
What we want is that every time we want to select 64, of this data. Okay.
Pass them.
To the model.
Make the forward, so get an output, so we get y.
We compare white with white hats.
Using the.
Loss function as a 3.
Then, thanks to this, we do the bad word to the model.
So we can update the weights of the model. Okay? And what we have done here is what we call one step. Okay? Because all the ways of my model has done one step. Okay.
Then, of course.
In this sense we only have considered 64 over all the data that we have. Okay, without 2040 data.
So then what we do is they take the next 64, do the forward, evaluate the loss, do the back port.
Another step, and we continue like that, and until we don't finish all our data that we have here once that we are done so okay, we have completed the support ebook. Okay, so we have completed one epoch of training.
So while you hear the model has been trained for 10 ebooks. Okay, what does it mean is that the model has seen all the data of my training data set 10 times okay, and every epoc is proposed by several steps.
That, of course, in this case is 64.
4, 2,048. Okay, is the number of steps total.
Why do you see.
What did that allow their do? Okay, is all of this again in an automatic group. So the only thing that we have to give to our data. Loader is okay. This is my data set.
This is the best size I would like to compare. Okay, and what does that allow them to do every night is it shuffles the data. Okay? If you want it, shuffles the data.
Then he said, Okay, let's take the 1st 64, then the next 64, 64, 64, 64. Then you wish, yeah.
To the pipeline and say, Okay, the airbox is finished.
What happened the data loader again along you'll tell you anything, shuffled the data. Okay, of course, shuffle the data. And in the rows, Not the x in the Y, to shuffle the rows.
And then we start again with another ebook in such a way that between the different epochs the data's the model.
Don't see the points in the same order. Okay.
That's the principle, because, of course, these halves with the stochastic guardian descends to try to generalize a little bit better.
So chaining loop.
As I already said, Forward, pass, okay. So we compute the prediction.
We then, with our true value. Okay, to label, we compute the loss. So we see how far is my model from computing I mean from giving back the right prediction.
Then once that I have this.
I do the backpropagation.
So I evaluate the gradients. I do the backpropagation. I update the parameters.
Using words. I mean it's written there using myoptimizer so very propagation. I have the direction, then I have to do the step.
With the optimizer that tests the model how to do the step, and once that is done so.
I see what the gradient so I delete from the model all the direction that he has seen during the last step. And I repeat this for all the batches and all the epochs. Okay.
So at the end of the day we have something like this: when we want to train our model.
So we train our model for several epochs. Okay, that are this one: okay, that we select is a number that we select.
Okay, this is the loss. Of course, the loss is something very important to keep track of, because the loss.
Is what tells you. How well the model is going. Okay, so closest to 0 is your loss better. The model is going. So what we imagine is that our model during the training will follow a loss that starts from a high number, and then converge hopefully to 0 .
And then here.
So in this second for loop we have the so-called step, the one that I called before step. So when I have a step. What I do, what I do is ask to the train data loader. Okay. To give me one input and to give me the input and the labels. Okay.
So here I mean, of course, because I didn't want something.
Okay.
As you can see here in the training, the loss is going to 0 . That is what we expect. Thanks to the data set that we have created, and to the model that we have created. Now we are making the linear model learn exactly that function that I was showing you before.
So what we have here for each step we get all the inputs and the labels. Okay.
For this particular batch, so I mean we can print inputs.
Shape. I mean it's fine because we are super late. So here I want to.
Also collect.
How.
Upgraded the loss, the weights and the biases.
Lost weight biases. That, of course, what I have to do then here is to.
Save them so losses not bad. Thank you very much.
Wait a pens. Okay, so this is what I we already have seen. Okay, so what now? What I want to show you.
Yeah, what I want to show you is how at every step.
The loss is updated. Okay, the wait is updated, because, as I already said, we are starting from a random initial point and, then we want the model the, linear model to, converge to a weight equal to.
Equal to.
5. Because this is what we have.
This is how we created our training data set. And then the same thing with the bias. Okay.
So.
Input label shape. Okay, I would like to have here a black.
Black.
Okay. So here in our training, I mean in our data, loader, we have set.
The bad side is equal to 256. Ok.
And so what we have here is that every time that I get one new batch from my data loader. What I expect is our X to be equal to 256, one. Okay, and our Y. So our labels.
Equal to $256, one again.
We move our data to the gpu. Okay, since we push before our model also in the gpu, because very important thing when you do a training when you do everything.
All the elements that you are using. So all the tensor that you are using must be in the same device. Okay. So if my model is in Gpu, I have to move 1st my data to Gpu and then use them. Okay.
Then I apply the 0 grad. So I remove the gradient from the from the step that we had before.
Then we do the forward, so we get.
The outputs from the model. Okay, given the inputs very easy.
Then we use the criterion that we have defined also before.
To compare the outputs that we got with the labels that we have. Okay. In this way we have the loss.
Then with the loss we do the backwards. So we compute the gradients over the model.
And once that we have the gradients we ask the model to make the step. So here is where we update our model. Okay.
Then we collect here some information. But it's not very important, and we say, Okay, our step is finished. Let's go to the next step. Next step again.
The data loaded on its own will give you back the next batch. Okay? And then you do the same. You move the data to the gpu. You do the forward. I mean you zeograd, This time because, from the before step we have some gradients saved.
And then we do exactly the same. Then automatically, the data loader. Once that we have finished our best, we say Ok.
We are at the end, so we can go out from the for loop. We go out from the for loop. We print the loss, and then we say, Okay, we have finished one epoch. Let's go with the next one.
Simple as that.
And.
And since I already have run this, I have to run it again.
But maybe without all these prints.
Okay here, as I already said, as you can see, the loss is not moving at all, because I'm not.
Okay. Here, as you can see, we have a random initialisation of the model so. At the beginning the loss is very high, and then going on with the epox, it becomes slower and lower. Okay? And here I have simply some plots of something that somehow.
Was expected. Okay, here. What I'm plotting is the loss. So how big are the mistakes that my model is making, then how is updated the only way that my linear model has, and how is updated my, the only bias that my model has, and, as we can see.
As expected.
When the loss goes down. So the model is making less mistakes. Okay.
The weight and the bias are converging to the actually expected value that we have crafted from our data set. So our weight go to 5, because the model is learning that this is.
Delinea interpolation that he has to make. My bias goes to 3, and the loss goes to 0 .
And, in fact, now, if we print again, we have something close to 5 as a waiting, something close to 3 as.
Habiles.
Now. 1st model training. Okay, I'm going quite long.
So I will go through that a little bit faster in such a way that I will give you a hint of what from now on the lab is about. Okay? And then you can finish it at home.
But here, anyway, the idea is that we will use exactly everything that we have learned until now, and that's the reason why I wanted to spend a lot of time on this very 1st part of the laboratory. Because now what I want to show you is the fact that, okay, now that we have learned how a data set work and what a data set is, how a data loading works.
How can I create my neural network? How, can I handle my training loop, etc.
Then we say, Ok. Now, I mean, we were dealing with a very, very, very easy problem. Okay, one input one output, and that's it.
Now, if we want to move, for example, to an image data set okay. So.
We have an image, and we want the model to learn if that image is a cat, an airplane, or a dark.
Almost everything that we have to do is exactly the same. Okay, it's almost exactly the same everything. So again here. You can see, okay, we download our data set. We create our data loader in exactly the same way. Okay.
Here we are telling them the data loader to shuffle.
Every time that we go through the whole data set.
Here. Namwork is actually not very important, but it's simply.
How much core of the gpu you I mean, your data loader, can use in parallel in order to access the data.
Of course, it's not working.
And here, if we try to get the next either of our train data loader, we will see that.
no, I have to download the data set for real.
that's bad!
We will have, anyway, something very similar, with the only difference that now our ex is not anymore just 1 point, but is one image. So you will see that.
Your X will be equal to what? To the image times, the number of image that you have, and the image. What does it means that every image in this data set that is called C. 5.
Is 32 times 32.
That is how the images did. And then for each image we have 3 different channels: Lgb: channels: okay. Because they are colored image. So what does it mean? We have 30 to our data final data set.
That's very likely I will never download, since it is at 1% after 1 min.
Ah!
Yeah.
Will be equal to 32 times 32 times 3. That is one image, as I said, Okay, maybe a low-in can help. But let me see if there is any message not amazing.
So 32.
Then if I have 1,000 images, times 1,000. Okay? Because I have all this information for each.
For each image. I want to show what I want to show you here you from now on.
Is the fact that I've already said I mean here you have some beautiful, visualizations transformation that you can make to your own images, and I would say that this is secondary. I mean, it's something that I suggest you to go through.
But it's very easy to get it so. The idea is simply that in order to avoid to make the model during imagine that I so in my model for 100 epox. Okay. In order to avoid to make the model see 100 times exactly the same image.
We have the so-called transformations, the transformations simply what do they do is that every time that you get the image, you apply a random transformation to the image so. A slight rotation or, you flip the image or, you change the detail you. Change the color and so many other stuff.
I mean the only.
Good thing here is that you can play a little bit with them, and they're fun in transforming images of different stuff but it's I mean, very, very straightforward, because again.
Simply we have the task form. Okay, so what we do is that we create our transformation pipeline. So we say, Okay, every time that you get the image the image must go through all these transformations. And and that's it. So.
I get the imaging I apply a random horizontal flip i. Apply a random crop i transform. It to a tensor. I normalize it, and that's it. Okay. It's not very interesting for what we want to do.
Second important thing. Along the labs. There are also some extra exercises, that, of course, also this one are part of the exercises that if you want, you can do through all my song will suggest you to do so, at least to read them.
They don't require a lot of time, but, as you can see.
In 1 h and a half there is a lot of information that we have to go through. Okay? And so we have selected like different levels of the information. There are some things that I think are absolutely mandatory to tell you, so everything that we have said until now was totally mandatory, because at least now hopefully.
Do. You have an idea of how our training pipeline works? That is what you will use for the rest of the semester. Then there are other things that, of course, are nice, extra interesting to see, but, of course, for a large language model course.
We will never ask you about the different transformation that you can apply to an image. Okay, that's the the thing.
And here, now from Nowhorn.
I want to show you something that we will use a lot in the next lab when we talk about Nlp models. Okay. Because one of the very big limitations that Nlp models has to respect to normal linear layer model or resness. For example, so simple convolutional.
Player networks is the fact that in order to performed well, they require a big, big, big pre-training okay, and the pre-training is something that.
For sure we will never do doing this course, because it's something that requires.
a lot of computational power, a lot of money, a lot of data, a lot of resources that, of course, we don't have. But it's not just us. I mean, the 99% of the population doesn't have, okay?
only be a very big company actually do the pre-training of our model, and then what we do is that we take from the shelf the model,
We apply some fine-tuning depending on the task that we want to solve, and then we actually can deploy the new model, okay? I want to make you a very easy example that is BERT, okay?
How many of you knows about BERT?
Okay, BERT, okay, very few. So, I will go super fast.
Where it is an encoder-only model for NLP. What does it mean? It means that it's a model that is trained simply
to transform an input text, okay, in numerical information. Then this numerical information, 99% of the times,
go through a classification layer, it actually makes some classification. So, imagine…
Very easy example. I want to do a sentiment analysis task, okay? So I have…
tons of reviews, okay? And I want to classify them between positive and negative, okay? I use BERT as an encoder to guess the information out
Get the information out from the text, okay? And then I add at the end a simple classification layer, so a simple linear layer that converts that information, that is the LAT and space information that we are going to
see what that space information means.
of our birth to the class…
Positive, negative. Simple like that. What is the problem? The problem is that, of course,
paired in order to understand the language,
needs a lot of examples, okay? Because imagine that you have to train a model, so just some random weights and biases,
In such a way that he can configure my input text in something that is numerically
meaningful. Of course, I need a lot of data, okay?
And of course, it's something that we cannot do.
So, birds come to us pre-trained.
So, the bets that we use, actually, doesn't random weights, okay, but what Bears has
uh… I mean, Beta already has, uh, has gone through freight training, okay? That was done, for example, by Meta, or by Google, or whatever. Okay, so the model already have seen a lot of data. So the model already knows about the language, that's the thing, okay? The Wiz that we have when we load belt are not random ways.
Okay? And now we have a beautiful block that allows us to transform the text in something numerically meaningful, okay? So what we do, usually,
is, okay, we add a classification layer at the end to our beautiful, uh…
build, and what we do is simply to learn a mapping between what birds understand
and our binary class, okay?
So what does it mean? It means that instead of having to…
To make the model, in my fine-tuning, learn about the language, the meaning of the words, all this stuff, plus
My classification task that is positive-negative, I only have to do the second one. So, I have my beautiful bird block, okay?
And then they already knows about the language, and then at the end, our linear. They simply take the Latin information of our bet and say, yes,
Notes. And this yes-no, again, go through a loss function, is exactly what we had already have seen.
So, what happened? We have an input data that is one sentence,
The input sentence goes through our encoder model, okay? They transform the sentence into something that is numerically meaningful, so this
From here, it come out. Attenth of Dimension, I don't know, 256.
Then I want to learn mapping,
between this tensor and the two classes, okay?
And here…
We asked two things, actually, that we can do.
Because…
Here, Bert has a lot of weights, okay? I mean, Bert needs a lot nowadays. Uh, but let's say that Bert, of course, has a lot of weights, okay? And the thing is that these weights are already pre-trained, okay?
So we have two ways of actually solving this task, okay? And this is what I want to show you
I mean, that I will not show you, uh, doing the rest of the lab, but as I already said,
The rest of the lab is exactly the same. So, every time you will create
Uh, your neural network.
You will prepare your dataset,
And then you will apply… I mean, this is a validation, but you will then apply the training of the model, okay?
And then again, Lord and Suin on CFAR10. This is just to show you that I'm not lying.
Here, we are using our SNET18, that you can consider it as the equivalent of images of birds, let's say.
And you can see that when you load the model, you can load it all with random weights.
Or, that is the last part of the lab.
within my, oh, okay, I have to complete here.
But of course, I mean, it's the same action.
It's the same, but I can, uh, ask to…
load the model with elevated weights.
Bye-bye.
Maybe, like, that was easier.
Okay, so here I can put some weights,
example, the first with Software IceNet.
And that's it. But what I want to show you from now on in this lab is that what you will do is to try to make different trains.
Okay? The very first one is, okay, I have a model,
With random weights, okay, and I try to learn the task of CIFAR10, okay? Then what I do after is I take the model,
With the pre-trained weight, so imagine that your ResNet
or your birth has already seen a lot of images, or a lot of text, okay? So it already knows
high level, what a dog is, what a cat is, or here, he already knows what is the meaning of the words, and so on.
And then what we try to do is to…
do two different things, okay?
Actually, three. The first one is, first, we try to train the model from scratch with just our computational power, okay? And you will not get good results, because you will need a long 20.
The second thing is that we try to
take a pre-trained model, so a model that already knows about stuff, and I try to fine-tune the model on top, okay? And what you will notice is that anyway for big models, you need a lot of time for the training, because every time you have to upload not only this,
But also, all the ways of our birth, okay?
The first, uh, said example that I show you at the very end,
is, let's try to do something else. Do you have call at the very beginning of our lecture the famous required class?
Likely not. I suggest you to go at the beginning of the lab, but anyway, what we try to do is to freeze our belt,
in this case. So, our model, and it just updates the final layer, because we are saying, okay, this model already knows about stuff.
Okay? What I would like to learn is simply the mapping between the number that this model outputs
And my very, very specific task, okay?
In this case, it's very simple. So, what do we have? Is that when we do the backpropagation, we just go here, we don't have to go to the beginning of our model, so we update much fewer weights, and what I want to show you with these three examples is the fact that, of course, having a pre-trained model is much better, because it allows you
to which, um…
I see it's loading, uh, to, um, reach the convergence much faster, okay?
But not only, also the fact that
We have more or less the same results, even if we just update the very final
layer, classification layer, keeping all the main, uh, model frozen.
But these allow us to get almost the same results, but in much, much, much, much, much fewer time, okay? Because, of course, here, we have to compute the gradient only for this,
And then we have to do the best of all employees. And so we are not choosing out all of this.
Okay?
The very final last part of the lab is something that you already have seen during the lecture, that I want to spare you after 1 hour and a half here.
That is, how back propagation works. I mean, the only cool thing that I want to show you
Because for what concern the mathematics, I can leave it…
to Flavio, and I'm more than happy to do so, is the fact that, as you can see, when you create your Tosh tensor note, and you put a require grad equal to, then you do some operation,
You do some operation, and automatically, automatically, you can see then with the make dots,
um… Torch will evaluate all the computation algorithms, okay?
So this is something that is automatically created by Torch.
It is exactly what you've already seen, how you already have seen this image, right? At the beginning of the week. Amazing.
This is simply something that is automatically done by Torch, okay? I just wanted to show you this, but this is less important. I strongly suggest you to go through
the Exercise 2 of the lab. I'm sorry that I went a little bit fast on that.
But as I already said, if you got the first part, okay,
Here, it's doing exactly the same way
Uh, the same thing, but…
I mean, shaving a little bit with hyperparameters, models, etc. So, it should be very straightforward. Then again,
If you have any question, of course, you can ask me.
at the end of the next lecture, in which hopefully we will be much faster.
But, of course, if you need, you can also text me, okay? I am Claudio Savelli, my email is claudio.savelli at polito.t, so if you have any doubt about the…
about the lab, please text me and I will try to answer as soon as possible, okay?
Do you have any question? But I don't think so, because you have any… okay, you are coming, okay. Just one second, I want to see, do you have any questions, or is it fine?
Okay, if you have any question, please come here so that I can leave the floor to the next professor. Excuse me, it was before you. It's a transformer.
debates model, yeah, but the simplest one.
In further parts. Yeah. So, the question is that, what the specific encoder, I mean…
why we hold the actual feeling, like, the different lines up the bed.
Why we force these, huh? Yeah, yeah. Okay, I mean… Look, guys, let me…
Yeah, yeah, okay, okay, okay.
specific properties are included on the bed?
Yeah, yeah, yeah,
And we talked about…
And in the portrayed in there, you do two different tasks.
Uh, lining specifically, not my specification. Lastly, what is called master language model. And you will understand that students use 2.
The more that we learn how the language works, okay? So, when I talk with you, okay, you can understand me, because you know the language. This is what bears out.
for different functions available, anyway. No, no, no, it was only for them. Bank is only for them.
No, no, no. I mean, not the Air Transformers, but they are similar to that, but BERT is a betrayed Transformer product. Okay. Language, but… Yeah, exactly. Because if we're training, bad testing only, that's the thing. So it only knows about left. Then, then the same architecture, I agree with you.
Exactly, exactly. But that bird is lent.
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
Nothing, nothing.
Okay,A lot of.